<?xml version="1.0" encoding="windows-1250" ?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="style.xsl" ?>
<content lang="en" id="documentation" subid="howto">
    <h1>How to write your own Filter</h1>

    <h5>Why would I want to write a Filter?</h5>

    <p>Filters are a way to eliminate unnecessary logging messages and prevent them 
        from reaching log <link href="targets">targets</link>. NLog comes with
        pre-defined filters that operate on string layouts and support most
        common operators. You need your own filter if none of the <link href="filters">provided filters</link>
        are suitable for your purpose.
    </p>

    <h5>How to write a filter?</h5>
    <p>
        It's really easy. Create a class that inherits from <code>NLog.Filter</code> 
        and override the <code>Check()</code> method. This method should return one of the following:
    </p>
    <p>
        <ul>
            <li><code>FilterResult.Neutral</code> - The filter doesn't want to decide whether the message should be logged. Further filters (if any) should be invoked to check.</li>
            <li><code>FilterResult.Ignore</code> - The message should NOT be logged</li>
            <li><code>FilterResult.Log</code> - The message should be logged. No further filters will be invoked.</li>
        </ul>
    </p>
    <p>
        Typically it's up to the user to decide what to do with the message after the filter matches. 
        Each filter has a <code>Result</code> that contains user-requested filter result for such a case. Filters 
        that would like to support user-configurability should return <code>Result</code> or <code>FilterResult.Neutral</code>.
    </p>

    <h5>Example</h5>
    <p>This is an example filter that eliminates messages sent between the specified hours.</p>
    <p>
        <code>csc.exe /t:library /out:MyAssembly.dll /r:NLog.dll MyFirstFilter.cs</code>
    </p>

    <code lang="C#" src="examples/MyFirstFilter.cs" />

    <h5>How to use the newly created layout renderer?</h5>
    <p>
        It's easy. Just put the renderer in a DLL and reference it from the the config file using the <x><extensions /></x>
        clause as described <a href="config.html#extensions">here</a>.
    </p> 

    <h5>Configuration file example</h5>
    <p>
        This example causes all messages between 10:00 and 12:59 to be ignored. Simple isn't it?
    </p>

    <code lang="xml" src="examples/config10.nlog" />

    <h5>How to pass configuration options to the filter?</h5>

    <p>
        Consider the above example. There are properties called "FromHour" and "ToHour" that do just that. 
        Having a public property that sets the required configuration parameters is enough for NLog to use it. 
        Each attribute that you put in the filter definition gets passed to the appropriate public property. 
        NLog takes care of the appropriate conversions necessary so that you can use integer, string, datetime, 
        boolean parameters. The parameters are case-insensitive.
    </p>

    <x><filters> ... <hourRange fromHour="10" toHour="12" action="Ignore" /> ... </filters></x>

    <p>sets the FromHour property to 10 and ToHour to 12 during configuration. To pass more parameters, just use more attributes:</p>

    <x><filters> ... <hourRange p1="" p2="" p3="" p4="" pN="" action="Ignore" /> ... </filters></x>

    <h5>Do I really need to create a separate DLL?</h5>

    <p>
        Not really. You can use FilterFactory.AddFilter() to register your layout renderer programmatically. 
        Just be sure to to it at the very beginning of your program before any log messages are written.
        It should be possible to reference your EXE using the <x><extensions /></x> clause.
    </p>

    <code lang="C#" src="examples/AddFilter.cs" />
</content>

