<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="style.xsl" ?>
<content lang="en" id="documentation" subid="howto">
    <h1>How to troubleshoot logging problems</h1>
    <p>If you have trouble getting NLog to work properly you may want to enable some debugging
        output to see what may be going wrong. This document describes the available internal debugging 
        features of NLog.</p>
    <h4>Enabling internal logging</h4>
    The following variables can be used to control NLog internal debugging:
    <p><code>NLOG_INTERNAL_LOG_TO_CONSOLE</code> - if this variable is found in the environment 
        NLog outputs internal logging information to the console using <code>Console.WriteLine</code>.</p>
    <p><code>NLOG_INTERNAL_LOG_FILE</code> - if this variable is found in the environment 
        NLog outputs internal logging information to the specified file. The file must be writable
        by the current user or it will not be created.</p>
    <p><code>NLOG_INTERNAL_LOG_LEVEL</code> - sets the internal logging level. The available values
        are <code>Debug, Info, Warn, Error, Fatal</code> - the default is <code>Info</code> which should
        be appropriate for most cases, to get more detailed logging - set it to <code>Debug</code>.</p>
    <h4>Enabling internal logging using the environment variables</h4>
    There are two cases here - setting the variables for an interactive process or for a service process.
    <h5>Enabling internal logging in the interactive processes</h5>
    <p>This case is easy. Just open the command prompt (<code>cmd.exe</code>), set your variables using
        the SET command and run your program. Here's the example:
    </p>
    <pre style="background-color: black; color: yellow; font-family: Courier New;padding: 10px; width: 80%">
        Microsoft Windows [Version 5.2.3790]
        (C) Copyright 1985-2003 Microsoft Corp.

        C:\MyApp&gt;set NLOG_INTERNAL_LOG_FILE=c:\temp\mylog.txt

        C:\MyApp&gt;set NLOG_INTERNAL_LOG_LEVEL=Debug

        C:\MyApp&gt;myapp.exe
    </pre>
    <h5>Enabling internal logging in the service processes</h5>
    <p>TO BE WRITTEN</p>

    <h4>Enabling internal logging programmatically</h4>
    <p>TO BE WRITTEN</p>
    <last-changed-date>$LastChangedDate$</last-changed-date>
</content>
