<?xml version="1.0" encoding="windows-1250" ?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="style.xsl" ?>
<content lang="en" id="index">
    <h3>What is NLog?</h3>
    <p>
        NLog is a .NET logging library similar in concepts to <a href="http://log4net.sourceforge.net/">log4net</a>, 
        designed with simplicity and flexibility in mind. NLog project is hosted at <a href="http://sourceforge.net/projects/nlog">sourceforge.net</a>.
    </p>

    <h3>Features</h3>
    <ul>
        <li>.NET, .NET Compact Framework and Mono 1.0 support</li>
        <li>very easy to configure, both with a config file and programmatically</li>
        <li>easy to use - interface is identical to <code>Console.WriteLine</code> - there's no need to use <code>String.Format</code> any more</li>
    </ul>

    <h3>Current Status</h3>
    <p>
        NLog 0.5 has been released in source and binary form. It's open source, licensed 
        under the terms of <a href="http://www.opensource.org/licenses/bsd-license.php">BSD license</a>, 
        which permits commercial use. Everyone is encouraged to test it and report feedback to the mailing list.
    </p>
    <p>
        The logging API is really minimal and shouldn't change in the future. Configuration API isn't ready yet, but 
        the configuration file support should be pretty usable. The support for .NET CF is in subversion but no packages
        are available yet. They will be, when it receives some testing and positive feedback from the community.
    </p>

    <h3>Documentation</h3>
    <ul>
        <li>To see NLog in action, open the <a href="tutorial.html">NLog Tutorial</a>.</li>
        <li>NLog API documentation generated using <a href="http://ndoc.sourceforge.net/">NDoc</a> is available <a href="help/">here</a>.</li>
        <li>See the <a href="config.html">Configuration Options</a> document for information on configuring NLog.</li>
        <li>Appender configuration is described in detail in the <a href="appenders.html">Appender Reference</a>.</li>
        <li>Layout Appender configuration is described in detail in the <a href="layoutappenders.html">Layout Appender Reference</a>.</li>
        <li>Filters are described in  the <a href="filters.html">Filter Reference</a>.</li>
        <li>If you have problems getting NLog to work, see <a href="troubleshoot.html">Troubleshooting NLog</a>.</li>
        <li>For a list of frequently asked questions and answers, see the <a href="faq.html">FAQ</a> section.</li>
    </ul>
</content>
