<?xml version="1.0" encoding="windows-1250" ?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="style.xsl" ?>
<content lang="en" id="introduction">
    <h1>Welcome to NLog</h1>
    <p>
        NLog is a free logging platform for .NET with rich log routing and management 
        capabilities. It makes it easy to produce and manage high-quality logs 
        for your application regardless of its size or complexity.
    </p>
    <p>
        It can process diagnostic messages emitted from any .NET language, augment
        them with contextual information, format them according to your preference 
        and send them to one or more targets such as file or database. 
        .NET, C/C++ and COM interop APIs are supported so that all your application components 
        including legacy modules written in C++/COM can route their log messages through a 
        common engine. 
    </p>
    <p>
        NLog is open source, licensed under the terms of <a href="http://www.opensource.org/licenses/bsd-license.php">BSD license</a>, 
    </p>
    <p>
        <a class="download" href="http://www.nlog-project.org/download.html"><span>Download Now For Free</span></a>
    </p>
    <h5>Project News</h5>
    <ul>
       <li><b>2009-09-07</b>&#160;<a href="http://nlog.codeplex.com/Release/ProjectReleases.aspx?ReleaseId=32601">NLog 1.0 Refresh</a> has been released.</li>
       <li><b>2009-09-06</b>&#160;NLog has moved from CodePlex from SourceForge.net. Source and binary releases as well as 
       the issue tracker will be hosted here. NLog documentation and Subversion repository will continue to be hosted on nlog-project.org. 
       Existing issues reported on sourceforge.net have been migrated to the "Issue Tracker".</li>
    </ul>
    <p>NLog can write log output to many targets including:</p>
    <ul>
        <li><b>Files</b> - single file or multiple, with automatic file naming and archival</li>
        <li><b>Event Log</b> - local or remote</li>
        <li><b>Database</b> - store your logs in databases supported by .NET</li>
        <li><b>Network</b> - using TCP, UDP, SOAP, MSMQ protocols</li>
        <li><b>Command-line console</b> - including color coding of messages</li>
        <li><b>E-mail</b> - you can receive emails whenever application errors occur</li>
        <li><b>ASP.NET trace</b></li>
        <li>... and many more</li>
    </ul>

    <p>Other key features:</p>
    <ul>
        <li>very easy to configure, both through <link href="config">configuration file</link> and programmatically</li>
        <li>easy-to-use logger pattern known from log4xxx</li>
        <li>advanced routing using buffering, asynchronous logging, load balancing, failover, and more</li>
        <li>cross-platform support: .NET Framework, .NET Compact Framework and Mono (on Windows and Unix)</li>
        <li>multiple APIs: <link href="netapi">.NET</link>, <link href="comapi">COM</link>, <link href="capi">C/C++</link></li>
    </ul>
</content>
